Previously, we listed the four main aspects of analyzing quantitative data;
قبل ذلك، أدرجنا الأربع جوانب الرئيسية لتحليل البيانات الكمية؛
center, spread, shape and outliers.
وهي الوسط والانتشار والشكل والقيم الخارجية.
We also looked specifically at measures of center,
وأمعنا النظر في مقاييس المركز،
by introducing means, medians and modes.
عن طريق تقديم الوسط والمتوسط والأوضاع.
Before we look at measures of spread,
قبل أن ننظر إلى مقاييس الانتشار،
it's important to understand notation.
من الهام أن نفهم التدوين.
You might not even know it,
قد لا تعرفونه،
but you use notation all the time.
ولكنكم تستخدمون التدوين طوال الوقت.
Consider this example, of five plus three.
يُرجى الانتباه إلى هذا المثال، خمسة زائد ثلاثة.
Plus is an English word.
Plus كلمة إنجليزية.
This symbol is notation and its universal.
هذا الرمز هو رمز التدوين، وهو رمز عالمي.
Notation is a common math language used to communicate.
التدوين هو لغة رياضية شائعة تستخدم للتواصل.
Regardless, of whether you speak English, Spanish,
بغض النظر عما إذا كنتم تتحدثون اللغة الإنجليزية أو الإسبانية
Greek or any other language,
أو اليونانية أو أي لغة أخرى،
you can work together using notation as a common language to solve problems.
يمكنكم العمل معًا باستخدام التدوين كلغة مشتركة لحل المشكلات.
Like learning any new language,
مثل تعلم أي لغة جديدة،
notation can be frightening at first,
من الممكن أن يكون التدوين مخيفًا وصعبًا في البداية،
but it's an essential tool for communicating ideas associated with data.
ولكنه أداة أساسية لتوصيل الأفكار المرتبطة بالبيانات.
We will work together through some examples to assure you completely master this concept.
سنعمل معًا في بعض الأمثلة للتأكد من إتقانكم لهذا المفهوم تمامًا.